Register of the Juan Atilio Bramuglia Papers, 1935-1974
Hoover Institution Archives
Juan Atilio Bramuglia Papers,
1935-1974
92106
Bramuglia, Juan Atilio, 1903-1962
19 manuscript boxes, 11 oversize boxes (12.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, financial records, clippings, other printed matter, and photographs, relating to Argentine foreign relations and participation in the United Nations; political conditions in Argentina, especially the Peronist movement and the Partido Union Popular; and labor policy and legislation in Argentina under the regime of Juan Peron. Includes correspondence with Peron, and some papers of Carlos Atilio Bramuglia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Argentina-Politics and government--1943-1955.; Argentina-Politics and government--1955-1983.; Argentina.; United Nations--Argentina.; Labor policy--Argentina.; Labor laws and legislation--Argentina.; Peronism.; Partido Union Popular (Argentina)
Biography
1903 January 1 Born, Chascomús, province of Buenos Aires
1925 Receives doctorate in law, University of Buenos Aires
1929-1949 Head of the legal department and counselor, Unión Ferroviaria, an association of railroad employees
1942 Teaches at the faculty of law, University of Buenos Aires
1944 Director of the social welfare department, Secretariat of Work and Welfare
1945 Federal Intervenor, province of Buenos Aires
1946-1949 Minister of Foreign Affairs
1962 Died
Collection Contents
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1941-1974. (Box No. 1)
  Awards, bank statements, biographies, clippings, contract, correspondence, diplomas, homages, menu, musical scores, and programs, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General, 1948-1974. Biographies and homages (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Awards and diplomas, 1945-1958 (Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1941-1954 (Folder 3)
  - Contract, 1942 (Folder 4)
  - Financial records. Bank statements and correspondence. Includes some material relating to the heirs of Juan Atilio Bramuglia
    - 1956-1961 (Folder 5)
    - 1962-1965 (Folder 6)
  - Miscellany, 1945-1949. Menu, musical scores, and programs (Folder 7)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1941-1959. (Box No. 1-2)
  Letters arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - Unidentified, 1943 (Folder 8)
    - A-Z, 1941-1956 (Folder 9)
  - Cárcano, Rámon, 1944 (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - Lucero, Franklin, 1950 (Folder 2)
  - Marshall, George C., 1950 (Folder 3)
  - Menendez, Antonio José, 1944 (Folder 4)
  - Mercante, Domingo, 1957 (Folder 5)
  - Perón, Juan, 1947-1954 (Folder 6)
  - Quijano, Hortensio, 1945 (Folder 7)
  - Risso Goni, Nestor, 1945 (Folder 8)
  - Ruiz Moreno, César, 1956 (Folder 9)
  - Truitt, Max, 1949 (Folder 10)
  - Unsain, Alejandro, 1947 (Folder 11)
  - Valls, Rafael, 1943 (Folder 12)
  - Vitolo, Alfredo, 1959 (Folder 13)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1935-1961. (Box No. 2-5)
  Articles, notes, radio addresses, radio dramas, messages, speeches, and writings, arranged chronologically by title
  - Article on Argentine labor movement, n.d. Typescript (Box 2., Folder 14)
  - Article on Argentine politics, n.d. Typescript (Folder 15)
  - Articles on labor law, n.d. Typescript (Folder 16)
  - "La cultura," n.d. Typescript (Folder 17)
  - "Dolor de madre," n.d. Holograph (Folder 18)
  - "Episodios de los ultimos tiempos de Sarmiento y su muerte," radio drama, n.d. Typescript (Folder 19)
  - "Episodios del gobernador Sarmiento," radio drama, n.d. Typescript (Folder 20)
  - "Las ideas de Bramuglia sobre la actualidad argentina," n.d. Typescript (Folder 21)
  - "Mensaje de paz a las mujeres del mundo," n.d. Typescript (Folder 22)
  - Notes for speeches, n.d. Holograph (Folder 23)
  - Notes on labor law, n.d. Holograph (Folder 24)
  - "El panorama en que se produce la Revolución," n.d. Typescript (Folder 25)
  - "Pasado politico, económico y social," n.d. Typescript (Folder 26)
  - "La previsión social en el pais," n.d. Typescript (Folder 27)
  - "Sarmiento y Urquiza," radio drama, n.d. Typescript (Folder 28)
  - Speech on public health, n.d. Holograph and typescript (Folder 29)
  - Speech on re-establishment of relations with the Soviet Union, n.d. Holograph and typescript (Folder 30)
  - Speech on religion, n.d. Three typescript drafts (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - Speech on women's role in society, n.d. Two typescript drafts (Folder 2)
  - Speech to trade unionists, n.d. Typescript (Folder 3)
  - Speech to youth group, n.d. Holograph (Folder 4)
  - Speeches on Argentine politics, n.d. Twelve typescript texts (Folder 5)
  - Speeches on foreign policy, n.d. One holograph and fifteen typescript texts (Folder 6)
  - Speeches on relations between Argentina and Chile, n.d. Four typescript texts (Folder 7)
  - Speeches on social security, n.d. Three typescript texts (Folder 8)
  - Speeches to meetings of the Unión Ferroviaria, n.d.
    - Nine typescript texts (Folder 9)
    - One typescript (Folder 10)
  - "Viaje en el Medicis," n.d. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - Writing on labor law, n.d. Typescript (Box 4., Folder 1-2)
  - Writing on social security, n.d. Holograph and typescript (Folder 3)
  - "Interpretación inteligente y humana," radio address, 1935 August 11. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - Speech to railroad workers, 1937 June 10. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - "Episodios de la vida de Sarmiento durante su presidencia," radio drama, 1938. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - Speech on labor law, 1941 August 8 (Folder 7)
  - La previsión social argentina, 1942. Printed copy (Folder 8)
  - Speech on social security, 1944 June 24. Typescript (Folder 9)
  - Speeches on politics and society, 1945. One holograph and six tyepscript texts (Folder 10)
  - "Dos discursos," 1945 January. Printed copy (Folder 11)
  - Speech on federal intervention in Buenos Aires province, 1945 March 14 (Folder 12)
  - "Democracia y educación," speech, 1945 April. Printed copy (Folder 13)
  - "El nuevo derecho social argentino," speech, 1945 April. Printed copy (Folder 14)
  - Speech on federal intervention in Buenos Aires province, 1945 April 19. Printed copy (Folder 15)
  - Speech on federal intervention in Buenos Aires province, 1945 May 12. Printed copy (Folder 16)
  - Official message, 1945 June 4. Printed copy (Folder 17)
  - "Por la rendención del campesino argentino," speech, 1945 July. Printed copy (Folder 18)
  - Speech commemorating Conrado Villegas, 1945 August 25. Typescript (Folder 19)
  - "Propositos de gobierno," speech, 1945 October. Printed copy (Folder 20)
  - Speech commemorating Independence Day (United States), 1946 July 4. Typescript (Box 5., Folder 1)
  - "Nuestra soberania y el Acta de Chapultepec," speech, 1946 August 21. Printed copy (Folder 2)
  - Message commemorating the discovery of the Americas, 1946 October 12. Holograph (Folder 3)
  - Speech on relations with Uruguay, 1947. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - Speech to meeting of foreign ministers, Rio de Janeiro, 1947. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - Message to the Americas, 1947 April 14. Printed copy (Folder 6)
  - "Palabras a nuestra generación," interview, 1947 July 30. Typescript and correspondence (Folder 7)
  - Press conference, Rio de Janeiro, 1947 August 19. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 8)
  - Radio address, Rio de Janeiro, 1947 August 25. Printed copy (Folder 9)
  - Message to the peoples of Europe, 1947 August 26. Typescript (Folder 10)
  - "La palabra argentina," 1947 September. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - Press conference, Buenos Aires, 1947 September 9. Printed copy (Folder 12)
  - Speech to Pan American Health Organization, Buenos Aires, 1947 September 24. Printed copy (Folder 13)
  - Speech, Buenos Aires, 1947 October. Printed copy (Folder 14)
  - "Cervantes," speech, 1947 October 12. Typescript (Folder 15)
  - Speech on foreign policy, 1947 October 23. Printed copy (Folder 16)
  - "Mediación sobre la disputa de Berlín," interview, 1948 (Folder 17)
  - Declarations concerning the Islas Malvinas (Falkland Islands), 1948 February 26. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 18)
  - Radio address, Bogotá, 1948 April 4. Typescript (Folder 19)
  - Speech to Argentine senate, 1948 July 22. Typescript (Folder 20)
  - Speeches to United Nations meetings, Paris, 1948 September-October. One typescript and two printed texts (Folder 21)
  - Interview with French journalists, 1948 September 22. Typescript (Folder 22)
  - Interview with English journalists, 1949 February 5. Typescript (Folder 23)
  - "El doctor Unsain y el 'Ordenamiento de las Leyes Obreras Argentinas,'" 1952. Typescript (Folder 24)
  - Speech on politics, 1957 June 14. Typescript (Folder 25)
  - Speech commemorating Flag Day, 1957 June 20. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 26)
  - Radio address, 1957 July 20. Typescript (Folder 27)
  - Speech on politics, 1957 August 29. Typescript (Folder 28)
  - Press conference, Córdoba, 1957 November 30. Typescript (Folder 29)
  - Speech at national convention of the Unión Popular, Córdoba, 1957 December 1. Printed copy (Folder 30)
  - Speech to meeting of the Unión Popular, 1958 January 16. Printed copy (Folder 31)
  - Radio address, 1961 January 3. Typescript (Folder 32)
- MINISTERIO DE RELACIONES EXTERIORES Y CULTO FILE, 1946-1949. (Box No. 6-10)
  Article, cables, clippings, correspondence, decree, invitation, memoranda, minutes, plans, position papers, printed matter, proceedings, reports, statistics, and treaties, relating to Bramuglia's tenure as foreign minister, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General. Article, decree, invitation, plans, position papers, resolutions, and speeches (Box 6.)
    - 1946 (Folder 1)
    - 1947-1948 (Folder 2)
    - 1949 (Folder 3)
  - Cables, 1948-1949
    - General, 1948-1949 (Folder 4)
    - Argentina. Embasada (U.S.)
      - To Washington, 1949 (Folder 5)
      - From Washington, 1949 (Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1948-1949. See also OVERSIZE MATERIAL (Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 7.)
    - General, 1948-1949
      - Unknown (Folder 1)
      - A (Folder 2)
      - B (Folder 3)
      - C (Folder 4)
      - D (Folder 5)
      - E (Folder 6)
      - F (Folder 7)
      - G (Folder 8)
      - H (Folder 9)
      - I (Folder 10)
      - J (Folder 11)
      - K (Folder 12)
      - L (Folder 13)
      - M (Folder 14)
      - N (Folder 15)
      - O (Folder 16)
      - P (Folder 17)
      - Q (Folder 18)
      - R (Folder 19)
      - S (Folder 20)
      - T (Folder 21)
      - U (Folder 22)
      - V (Folder 23)
      - W (Folder 24)
      - Y (Folder 25)
    - Achmeteli, Michael, 1948 (Box 8., Folder 1)
    - Balfour, John, 1949 (Folder 2)
    - Blanco, Juan Carlos, 1948 (Folder 3)
    - Bruce, James, 1949 (Folder 4)
    - Cadogan, Alexander, 1948 (Folder 5)
    - Corominas, Enriqué
      - 1947
        - September-October (Folder 6)
        - November-December (Folder 7)
      - 1948-1949 (Folder 8)
    - Eden, Abba, 1948 (Folder 9)
    - La Rosa, Pascual, 1948 (Folder 10)
    - Mejia, Claudio, 1948 (Folder 11)
    - O'Donoghue, Sidney, 1947 (Folder 12)
    - Oviedo, Antonio, 1949 (Folder 13)
    - Sosa Molina, José Humberto, 1947-1948 (Folder 14)
    - Uriburu, Ernesto, 1946 (Folder 15)
    - Valenti, Saverio, 1947-1948 (Folder 16)
  - Memoranda, 1948 (Folder 17)
  - Minutes and proceedings
    - 1946 (Folder 18)
    - 1947. Interamerican Conference for the Maintenance of Continental Peace and Security, Rio de Janeiro (Folder 19-20)
    - 1947. Interamerican Conference for the Maintenance of Continental Peace and Security, Rio de Janeiro (Box 9., Folder 1-4)
    - 1948
      - National Chamber of Deputies, Buenos Aires (Folder 5)
      - Ninth International American Conference, Bogotá (Folder 6)
      - Meetings of the United Nations General Assembly and Security Council, Paris (Folder 7-8)
      - Meetings of the United Nations General Assembly and Security Council, Paris (Box 10., Folder 1)
  - Printed matter, 1946-1948. Pamphlets (Folder 2)
  - Reports
    - General, 1946-1948 (Folder 3-4)
    - Berlin Crisis, 1948 (Folder 5)
  - Statistics, 1949 (Folder 6)
  - Treaties
    - 1946 (Folder 7)
    - 1947 (Folder 8)
- PARTIDO UNIÓN POPULAR FILE, 1944-1974. (Box No. 10-12)
  Affidavits, by-laws, cables, charters, charts, circulars, clippings, correspondence, declarations, directives, election material, lists, memoranda, minutes, miscellany, platforms, press releases, proceedings, programs, and reports, concerning a political party of which Bramuglia served as president, arranged alphabetically by physical form. Includes some material relating to Carlos Atilio Bramuglia
  - General, 1957-1964. Directives, election material, memoranda, and miscellany (Box 10., Folder 9)
  - By-laws, charters, and resolutions, 1957-1972 (Box 11., Folder 1)
  - Cables, 1957-1974 (Folder 2)
  - Circulars, 1957-1960 (Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1956-1972 (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence
    - 1944-1958 (Folder 5)
    - 1959-1974 (Folder 6)
  - Declarations, manifestos, and messages, 1957-1958 (Folder 7-8)
  - Delegate and membership lists, n.d. (Folder 9)
  - Legal records, 1958-1973. Affidavits and correspondence (Box 12., Folder 1)
  - Minutes and proceedings
    - Undated (Folder 2)
    - 1957 (Folder 3)
    - 1958 (Folder 4)
    - 1961 (Folder 5)
    - 1963-1965 (Folder 6)
  - Organizational charts, n.d. (Folder 7)
  - Platforms and programs, 1957 (Folder 8)
  - Press releases, 1957-1973 (Folder 9)
- ACADEMIC FILE, 1942-1950. (Box No. 12-13)
  Bibliography, clippings, correspondence, lectures, list, notes, programs, plans, and schedules, relating to courses given by Bramuglia at various Argentine universties, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General, 1942-1948. Programs, plans, and schedules (Box 12., Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1947 (Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1950 (Folder 12)
  - Lectures
    - General, n.d.
      - Holograph notes (Folder 13)
      - Typescript text on labor law (Box 13., Folder 1)
    - 1942. Typescript (Folder 2)
    - 1947
      - July. Typescript text and printed copy. Includes correspondence and list of invitees (Folder 3)
      - August. Typescript text and printed copy. Includes bibliography and program (Folder 4)
    - 1948. Typescript and printed schedule (Folder 5)
- JUNTA NACIONAL DE COORDINACIÓN DE PARTIDOS REVOLUCIÓNARIOS FILE, 1946. (Box No. 13-14)
  Cables, charts, correspondence, election material, lists, memoranda, and reports, relating to a campaign organization of which Bramuglia was president, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General. Election material, lists, memoranda, and reports (Box 13., Folder 6)
  - Cables (Box 14., Folder 1)
  - Charts (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (Folder 3)
- SECRETARÍA DE TRABAJO Y PREVISIÓN FILE, 1942-1946. (Box No. 14)
  Decrees, forms, laws, memorandum, proceedings, regulations, reports, and statistics, concerning a goverment department in which Bramuglia worked, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Decrees, laws, and regulations, 1944-1945 (Box 14., Folder 4-5)
  - Forms, n.d. (Folder 6)
  - Memorandum, 1944 (Folder 7)
  - Proceedings, 1942-1944 (Folder 8)
  - Reports, 1944 (Folder 9)
  - Statistics, 1946 (Folder 10)
- UNIÓN FERROVIARIA FILE, 1937-1945. (Box No. 15)
  Affidavits, bulletins, circular, correspondence, leaflets, list, pamphlet, proceedings, and speeches, concerning an organization of railway employees with which Bramuglia served as legal counsel, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General, 1941-1944. Bulletins, circular, leaflets, list, pamphlet, and speeches (Box 15., Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1945 (Folder 2)
  - Legal records, 1943-1944. Affidavits and list (Folder 3)
  - Proceedings, 1937-1938 (Folder 4)
- CARLOS ATILIO BRAMUGLIA FILE, 1956-1974. (Box No. 15)
  Accounts, affidavits, charters, clippings, correspondence, declarations, invitation, judgments, receipts, and serial issue, concerning Juan Atilio Bramuglia's son, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Certificates and invitations, 1975 (Box 15., Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1974 (Folder 6)
  - Financial records, 1962-1968. Accounts, correspondence, and receipts (Folder 7)
  - Legal records, 1956-1962. Affidavits, correspondence, and judgments (Folder 8)
  - Printed matter, 1972. Serial issue (Folder 9)
  - Subject file - Partido Acción Popular. Affidavits, charters, clippings, and declarations, 1974 (Folder 10)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1941-1973. (Box No. 16-18)
  Clippings, election material, plans, printed matter, proceedings, reports, serial issues, and statistics, arranged alphabetically by subject
  Clippings, election material, plans, printed matter, proceedings, reports, serial issues, and statistics. Includes some material relating to Carlos Atilio Bramuglia
  - Argentina - Economic conditions (Box 16.)
    - Alcoholic beverage industry (Folder 1-5)
    - Inflation (Box 17., Folder 1)
    - Railroad industry (Folder 2-4)
  - Argentina - Politics and government
    - General (Folder 5-6)
    - Communism (Folder 7)
    - Peronism (Folder 8-9)
    - Peronism (Box 18., Folder 1)
  - Buenos Aires (Argentina: City), Buenos Aires (Argentina: Province) (Folder 2)
  - Comisión Interamericana de Mujeres (Folder 3)
  - Confederación General del Trabajo (Argentina) (Folder 4)
  - Moltedo, Juan (Folder 5)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL, 1947-1948. (Box No. 19-25)
  Albums of clippings documenting Bramuglia's tenure as foreign minister
  7 albums of clippings relating to Juan Atilio Bramuglia's tenure as foreign minister, including one (box 19) regarding his participation in the Interamerican Conference for the Maintenance of Continental Peace and Security, Rio de Janeiro, 1947, four (boxes 20-23) concerning his role in the Ninth International American Conference, Bogotá, 1948, and two (boxes 24-25) documenting official visits to Italy and the United Kingdom, 1948
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1948-1964. (Box No. 26)
  Albums of photographs depicting scenes of Bramuglia's career as foreign minister, as well as his personal residence
  Includes some material relating to Carlos Atilio Bramuglia. One album of 11 photographs showing Juan Atilio Bramuglia in the company of Juan Perón, Eva Perón, and President Luis Batlle Beres of Uruguay, and one album of 16 photographs depicting exterior and interior views of the Bramuglia family residence
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS (Box No. 27-30)